<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a Christian friend in the country to another in the city</title>
            <author>Ro. Bl.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3036</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12918</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11828019</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11828019</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49706</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28267)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 809:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a Christian friend in the country to another in the city</title>
                  <author>Ro. Bl.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Ro. Bl. by Wing.</note>
                  <note>A discussion of the government under Cromwell.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49706:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Letter from a Chriſtian Friend in the Country to another in the City.</head>
            <p>WEE had lately ſent downe into the Country De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations from the Protector (ſo called) and his Councel, holding forth the grounds and reaſons of their proceedings (as they pretend) for ſecuring the peace of the Common wealth, a thing very plauſible to palliate their aſſumed Power over us and our Poſteritie.</p>
            <p>We may wonder in the firſt place, at their Nick-naming us a Common-wealth, we being as under the yoak of an Arbitrary power, no better then ear board <hi>Ruſsian</hi> Slaves, they having by a ſeeming neceſſity abſolutely overthrown the honour, intereſt, and Freedom of the people of <hi>England,</hi> by the aboliſhing of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments; fruſtrating our Fundamental laws, Uſurping a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making power, leavying of money and Forces, Commanding War and Peace by Land and Sea, and making themſelves the onely determiners of guilt or innocence, of life or death, of law or liberty; as in the Caſe of the Caveleers Sequeſtration, to a Tenth and Fifteenth part of Rents and Goods, their Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish rule of proceeding doth very much diſſatisfie the Country, notwithſtanding all their ſmall Reaſons urged; in order to a pretended ſecuring the peace of the Common wealth (as they moſt miſerably miſcall us) upon occuſion of the late Inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Rebellion againſt themſelves, the greateſt Rebels, and moſt lawleſſe Uſurpers, that as yet any Hiſtory, ancient or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern, ever made mention of; whereby they are becom odious to us, notable and abominable all Europe over, and I wiſh it were as affectually convincing as accuſing in their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; that they have crucified the Cauſe of God and their Country, bet wixt theſe two State Thieves, Uſurpation and Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:49706:2"/>But our Lot (dear Sir) is fallen into that Age and part of the world, wherein the miſtery of Iniquity is working ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 28, 9, 10 He is now revealed, whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming is after the working of Sathan, with all powers and ſigns and lying wonders, and withall deceivableneſſe of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If we do but take a ſerious view of Antichriſt, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as he is the whole body, or as he is this or that part, we ſhall finde him in no other garbe then the form of a glorious Saint, not onely deceiving the blind and ignorant world, but as far as is poſſible even many of the very Elect themſelves, that which is the fore runner, or rather occaſion, as I may ſo ſay, (reſpecting the concurrences of Gods permiſſive providence) is mens not receiving the love of the Truth (not the profeſſion) for how many have profeſſed fairly upon a civill and Goſpel account. How many like <hi>Jehu</hi> have marched furiouſly, that are now fallen off, and have with <hi>Demas</hi> embraced the world? How many have declared for Liberty, againſt Tyranny, who are now become as great Uſurpers and oppreſſors as any? How many ſeeming ſelf deniers, are become incomparable ſelf-ſeekers? How have they in a Saint-like ſimplicity ſeemed to ſlight the glory and greatneſſe of the world, who cannot now be contented with leſſe then Principalities and Powers: Nay even with the very Attributes of God himſelf? what ſpecious pretenders were they for the kingdom of Chriſt, who are now become the Imprſoners and Perſecutors of the Profeſſors of it, and divers other true and faithfull Patriots, I mean, Mr. <hi>Feak,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rogers,</hi> Lt. Gen. <hi>Ludlow,</hi> M. <hi>G. Harriſon,</hi> M. G. <hi>Overton,</hi> Col. <hi>Rich,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cary,</hi> Quart. M. Gen. <hi>Courtney,</hi> Coll. <hi>Allured, &amp;c.</hi> and others, who by their means have been laid, or laid themſelves aſide, as Collonel <hi>Okey,</hi> Coll. <hi>Sanders,</hi> Major <hi>Wiggam, &amp;c.</hi> Do they not in their Declaration declare, one a deſigner, the other deſigned; indeed the Moderation of the words was deſigned is remarkable, it being diſproportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the policy they ſteer by, ſo tenderly to touch their reputations, whoſe ruines they reach at, their malice being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to have proved them ſuch offendors, if they could; but the ſervice and ſufferings of theſe men, are Arguments invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible of their innocence, untill by a fair and legall Tryall, we be convinced of the contrary; in the interim, words will not make the world believe what was not, neither will their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49706:2"/>
by ſuch means be ſo ſoon blaſted; eſpecially, when they confeſſe in their Declaration, they onely think them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe thoſe Engliſhmen had deſigned ſome endeavours for the making good their ingagements, and calling off the yoak of Tyranny, ſuppoſe they had invoked or invited the Army (backſlidden from the Cauſe of God and their Country) to return to their obedience, for the confirmation of our juſt Fundamental laws and Liberties, for the right placing of the Soveraign power of the People, in a lawfull Repreſentative, for relieving the oppreſſed and impriſoned, who groan for deliverance, from the bondage of theſe moſt mercileſſe Task-Maſters, had they not hereby approved themſelves brave and publique ſpirited Patriots; will not ſuch one day be received, with a well done, good and faithfull ſervants, where their and our, Oppreſſors ſhall ſtand with pale-faces, and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Conſciences, before that God, who will render to every man according to his works, who will appear aſ witneſs againſt the ſwearer and forſwearer, who will make Inquiſition for blood; who will call the Apoſtates and Hypocrites to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for all their perjuries and oppreſſions, hath not this <hi>Ell ſhaddy</hi> the moſt high God ever ſignally appeared againſt the proud and tyrannical <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> of the world, with all their projectors and Paraſites.</p>
            <p>In the interim, dear Friend, we may behold as in a glaſſe our preſent deplorable condition under a Government (as they call it) where the Will and intereſt of a State Junto is both law and evidence. At this rate, who may not be a deſigner and offender, and accordingly declared and puniſhed; who would have believed about eight or ten years ſince, we ſhould have ſeen ſuch lawleſſe and imparrallel'd Impious proceedings? who would have imagined that ſuch publique ſpirits as the perſons prementioned, ſhould ſo cauſeleſly be kept priſoners, by their fellow-ſervants, who pretended themſelves promoters, but have proved perverters of piety and publike liberty, perſons of the ſame ſpirit with <hi>Strafford, Canterbury, &amp;c.</hi> Nay, far worſe, who would have imagined, that our Aſſertors of Law and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty would without Baiſe or Mainprize, not onely incarſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Bodies of our aſoreſaid Friends, but alſo deny ſome of them the comfort of their neareſt and deareſt relations; a ſad
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49706:3"/>
requitall for their ſeverall faithful ſervices and ſufferings, they may in policy pretend what they pleaſe; but are not theſe things moſt abominable in the eyes of a righteous God, who although he hath an abſolute ſoveraignty over the world, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth none before they have ſinned, contrary to the laws of the Land, and the very practiſe of Heathens, who allowed <hi>Paul</hi> (whom they accounted more dangerous and ſeditious, then our Friends enemies can ſay they are) the enjoyment of his friends, 24 <hi>Act.</hi> 23. And he commanded a Centurian to keep <hi>Paul</hi> and to let him have liberty, and that he ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid none of his acquaintance (much leſſe wiſe and children) to miniſter or come unto him; yea, further ſaith <hi>Feſtus,</hi> the 25. <hi>chap. 27. v.</hi> 
               <q>For it ſeemeth to me unreaſonable to ſend a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and not withall to ſignifie the crime laid againſt him.</q> If we muſt after this manner exchange our juſt fundamental laws for their fundamentall reaſon, I believe when it is too late we may take up the Lamentation of the Prophet <hi>Iſai.</hi> 59. 14, 15. <q>And judgment is turned away backward, and juſtice ſtandeth afar off: For truth is fallen in the ſtreet; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea, truth faileth, and he that departeth from evill maketh himſelf a prey.</q> But let us comfort our ſelves in this, that our God will cauſe the pride of the arrogant to ceaſe, lay low the haughtineſſe of the terrible, and cut off all that watch for iniquity, that make a man an offender for a word, and lay a ſnare for him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth in the gate, and turn aſide the juſt for a thing of nought but ſay our friends adverſaries. Theſe men are ſeditious, faſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fellows, Railers, and Levellers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo are all who will not ſell and ſacrifice themſelves to work wickedneſſe: Let a man be of what principle or opinion he pleaſe, he is too high or too low, if he cannot play the paraſite; if he be ſincere, he is a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctary, if a lover of liberty upon a publique account, he is a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller. But was not the (Protector (ſo called) and many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men more in the Army and Nation ſuch, when the Army refuſed to disband at <hi>New Market:</hi> I cannot I profeſſ, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire that the Protector (ſo called) his Councel or Officers can without bluſhing make the leaſt mention of levelling, when they themſelves are the moſt monſtrous levellers, that ever yet bore the name of Engliſhmen: Have they not levelled Church and State, King and Parliament, Proprietics, Laws, Liberties, nay, what not? Do they not levell and lay low whatſoever
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49706:3"/>
ſtands in the way of their Arbitary intereſt, have they not made the moſt honourable Army in <hi>Europe,</hi> a crew of mercenary Cut-throsts, or Janizarics, have they not under pretence of preſerving the publique Peace, cantoniz'd the Countries, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing ſo many Major Generals (as they call them) to play <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudleys</hi> part, to run in the ſame path of Oppreſtion, untill perhaps they arrive at their reward. Now for thoſe men to call Levelling a crime, brings them under the condemnation of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 2. 1. &amp; 3. verſes: <q>Therefore thou art inexcuſable ô man, whoſover thou art that judgeſt, for wherein thou judgeſt another thou condemneſt thy ſelf, for thou that jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt doeſt the ſame things: And thinkeſt thou ô man that judgeſt them which do ſuch things, and doeſt the ſame; that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgement of God. Thou hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, firſt caſt the Beam out of thine own eye, and then ſhalt thou ſee clearly to caſt out the Moat out of thy Brothers eye.</q> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 5. But the Protectors (ſo called) great Plea for all his nefarious practiſes is Neceſſity, but I ſuppoſe this Cloak is worn ſo thrid-bare upon all procedures, that even thoſe who are but half-ſighted may ſee through it, how vertuall their neceſſity hath been ſince the purging of the old Parliament: let us a little conſider, Firſt for diſſolving of that Parliament they derive their neceſſity, as they ſay, from the Parliaments deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to perpetuate themſelves, whereas the truth is, they diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them, becauſe they were paſſing a Bill for a New Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative; as ſome Members our Country-men do to this day affirm. The Neceſſity for diſſolving the Little Parliament was, becauſe they would have regulated the Law, or framed a new Modell, more proportionable to the genius of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and conſiſtent with the intereſt of Chriſt, and done many other good things, for which the Officers of the Army had both Petitioned the former Parliament, and railed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them all the Nation over, becauſe they neglected the doing of them, how truly have they hereby manifeſted their neceſſity to be but hypocriſie: Nay is it not plain from the conſequence, that theſe changes were onely deſigned to uſhel in a greater; did they not by the reproaches they caſt upon the old Parliament, and by their electing men of contrary principles in the other, endeavour to inſinuate a neceſſity for diſcarding that form of Government.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49706:4"/>But ſuppoſe we ſhould grant a neceſſity for diſſolving the Parliament, yet what neceſſity is there upon the Nations ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to perpetuate an Arbitrary, unlimited power in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, to inſlave three Nations by a ſtanding Army of above 60000. men and an ignoble Militia of 10000. Horſe in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> doth not true neceſſity ariſe from the peoples ſafety; but how is that made good, when they have no other ſecurity for their Lives, Liberties and Properties, then the will of ſingle Perſon, flancked and fortified with a mercenary Army, and who either is or may be a Tyrant.</p>
            <p>Again, what other neceſſity have they to keep down all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, but to keep up their boundleſſe ambition, what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity was there when the Nation was almoſt exhauſted by Taxations, to ſpend 18 or 19. hundred thouſand pounds in a fruitleſſe expedition to <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> which they are again at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting notwithſtanding the Arm of the Lord hath of late been apparently made bare againſt them in that buſineſſe? Or what neceſſity is there to impriſon and continue impriſoned without tryall (contrary to the Laws of God and this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion their own voluntary Oathes and ingagements) the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervants of God and their Country? May we not hence plainly perceive they make their neceſſity as boundleſſe as their Ambition, as deſtractive as their deſire of Domination? What neceſſity is there to multiply unparaleld Taxes and Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſave in purſuance of their private plots and projects, to pick our pockets and purſes, that they may the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily oppreſſe us? we are conſtrained ſay ſome, by oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and poverty to bind the people unto peace and union, but is not poverty too poor a plant for ſuch fair fruit, as love and union to grow upon; doth not war rather then peace ſpring from want, which like an armed man is the Herauld or Fore-runner of Innovations, ſurely they that will keep a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple peaceable muſt not make them poor by oppreſſion; we are apt with others wounds to ſalve our own; plenty ſtuns men in ſecure repoſes, but oppreſſion makes a wiſe man mad: <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> would never have contrived his Countrys ruine, but to prevent his own; oh that there were no ſuch <hi>Catelines</hi> in our new Court, or rather that we had neither Court nor <hi>Cateline,</hi> nor any of that ſpirit, for which the laſt Parliament ſo called was pretendedly diſſolved, <hi>viz.</hi> For that they had an aking 100th againſt the godly party.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49706:4"/>The Cryes and complaints of the oppreſſed in this Nation I perceive grown great according to that of the wiſe-man, <hi>Prov. 29. 2.</hi> 
               <q>When the righteous are in Authority the people rejoyce, but when the wicked beareth rule the people mourn,</q> men of all rancks and capacityes (Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Officers and Courtiers excepted) make this addition to their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <q>How long Lord, holy and true will it be ere thou aveng, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other cauſes of this complaint, to ſpeake in the words of <hi>Solomon</hi> 30. Prov. 22. it is <q>becauſe of a ſervant when he reigntch.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Your trading I heare in the City is become and likely to continue ſo dead, that men who have not good ſtocks are ready to ſhut up ſhop. But your Condition in the City I beleeve is made better then ours in the Country, in reſpect both of Landlord and Tenent, the one can ſcarcely get any rent becauſe the other cannot raiſe it, Farmers proſeſſe they muſt give up their Farmes, becauſe the profit will not ballaſt the charge of tillage and Taxes: It was the vaine brag of <hi>Cajus Marius</hi> that hee ſate in the ruines of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and is it not the diſgrace of our grandees that they are grown great by the ruines of their Country, he was a Heathen and died mad, they are either Chriſtians or hypocrits, and may be more miſerable. How doth that heathen Romane <hi>Cato</hi> ſhame and out-ſtrip our pretended Chriſtian Patriots? he was as Anxious for the ſafety and freedome of <hi>Rome</hi> as they are ſolicitous for themſelves; he was as reall a refuge for afflicted virtue as they are oppreſſors of it. They engaged their lives and ſouls to get gain, but he laid down his life for liberty, chooſing rather to be his Countries Sacrifice then <hi>Caeſars</hi> Slave.</p>
            <p>Dear Friend, were all our Courtiers either Chriſtians or <hi>Cato's,</hi> they would rather Conquer for their Country then for themſelves; but oh, for what he dyed to preſerve, they live to ſpoil, and prey upon the blood of a whole War; the price of Widdows prayers, and Orphants tears proclaims their game to be their godlineſſe; oh, theſe are ſad fruits of our fourteen years fighting! poverty and oppreſſion are very uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable fruits of Reformation, but dominion impiouſly got, muſt be impiouſly kept; one ſin muſt maintain another; yet let us with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, conſider, that Jehovah is greater then the king of feirce counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and underſtanding dark ſentences, although he may for a time (which we hope is neer an end) by policy cauſe craft to proſper in his hand, and think to change Times and Laws, yet his Dominion ſhall be taken away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Did not our Lord in mercy caſt the late Kings yoak from off our necks. After that darkneſſe was diſpell'd did not the light of liberty dawne, untill tempeſtuous clouds ariſing from the filthy fogs of falſhood and treachery, impoſtumated in the Braines and Boſomes of ſome few inſtruments, in the work of Liberty? we were environed with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49706:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a more Egyptian darkneſſe then ever, hath not their treachery and our ingratitude urged God to repent of his favours? he ſent us light, but we loving darkneſſe rather than light, ſhut our eys againſt the Sun-beams that we might with more modeſty ſin in ſecret; He began to reſtore li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, but we rather choſe ſervitude: why ſhould we then complain, that we are enſlaved in unlimitted Monarchy, whileſt by a ſhamefull kind of villenage, we bow our ſervile necks under the baſeſt yoak, and pay our Homage to the moſt matchloſſe monſters of mankinde, that ever any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Nation truckled under? Yet dear friend, fear not, freedome will yet fall upon its ſect, in the interim pious and publique ſpirits may be foiled, but not defeated; great and good deſignes are carried on by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly additions, but ſudden elevations ſoon decline like aboutive Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brions; believe it our Lord will blaſt their baſe enſlaving deſignes, and nipt their Muſhrom honours in the bud, Hypocriſie may a little longer act vices part in vertues apparrel, but ſhall at laſt fall head long from its greateſt height: A tyrants Conſcience knows no night of reſt, blood in deſpight of <hi>Poppy</hi> breaks his ſleep, the fears and fury of his fantacy fix deaths unerring ſymptoms in his face; deſpair not, a Tyrants death is the people Antidote, in his own good time, our God will cure the Courtiers itch and avarice, let greatneſſe held by force fear a fall; height and preciptance ſtand tottering, and know no <hi>Mediums</hi> in their Declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Whoſoever obſerves the Orthodoxall maximes of our dayes need not marvel, that our Marſhaliſts have raviſh'd <hi>Aſtrea</hi> and pull'd juſtice down; but Chriſt Jeſus will come quickly, and bring his reward with him; the Saints ſhall ſit and ſee his righteous judgments: Nay, Mr. <hi>Feak,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rogers, &amp;c.</hi> ſhall judge their Oppreſſors and Perſecutors; but I doubt our State profeſſors, who have ſet themſelves over us, do no more believe this truth then <hi>Pilate</hi> when he was judging Chriſt did believe he was Condemning his judge, or the Jews when they were whipping, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting and impriſoning the Apoſtles, did thinke to ſee them ſit on twelve Throns, judging the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> do you not know ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> That the Saints ſhall judge the world: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2, 3. Oh that our careleſſe Courtiers and Army men (who with wings impt with the plumes of Oppreſſion and Perjury, ſoar over us like Eagles of a true Ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, whileſt indeed they are Birds of prey not of Paradiſe) would be now of the ſame mind, as they will be when they ſhall ſee <q>the heavens paſſe away with a noiſe, and the Elements melt with fervent heat <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> But when all is ſaid, <q>The wicked will do wickedly, but the wiſe ſhall underſtand and the prudent ſhall keep ſilence:</q> Dear Friend farewell, and let us hold faſt till our Lord come, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, co-expectant in the deliverance of Syon,
Ro. Bl.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb.</hi> 24. 1655.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
